<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Plaine truth without feare or flattery, or, A true discovery of the unlawfulnesse of the Presbyterian government it being inconsistent with monarchy, and the peoples liberties, and contrary both to the protestation and covenant : the end of establishing the militia of London in such hands as it is now put into by the new ordinance, the betraying votes and destructive practices of a traiterous party in the House of Commons concerning certain petions for liberty and justice : also, a vindication of His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, concerning certaine scurrulous words uttered by some of the said faction : with the meanes and wayes that must be used to obtaine reliefe against the said cyrannous usurpers, and for reducing the parliament to its due rights, power and priviledges, in the preservation of the kingdomes laws and liberties / written by I.L.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12426434</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12426434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 944:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Plaine truth without feare or flattery, or, A true discovery of the unlawfulnesse of the Presbyterian government it being inconsistent with monarchy, and the peoples liberties, and contrary both to the protestation and covenant : the end of establishing the militia of London in such hands as it is now put into by the new ordinance, the betraying votes and destructive practices of a traiterous party in the House of Commons concerning certain petions for liberty and justice : also, a vindication of His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, concerning certaine scurrulous words uttered by some of the said faction : with the meanes and wayes that must be used to obtaine reliefe against the said cyrannous usurpers, and for reducing the parliament to its due rights, power and priviledges, in the preservation of the kingdomes laws and liberties / written by I.L.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and published for the information, advice, and benefit of the poore, oppressed, betrayed, and almost destroyed Commons of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Lilburne. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671.</term>
               <term>Levellers.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Plaine Truth without FEARE OR FLATTERY: OR A TRVE DISCOVERY OF THE Unlawfulneſſe of the Presbyterian Government, it being inconſiſtent with Monarchy, and the Peoples Liberties; and contrary both to the Proteſtation and Covenant. The end of eſtabliſhing the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in ſuch hands as it is now put into by the new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. The betraying Votes, and deſtructive practices of a Traiterous Party in the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons concerning certain Petitions for Liberty and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A. Vindication of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> concerning certaine ſcurrulous words uttered by ſome of the ſaid Faction.</p>
            <p>WITH The meanes and wayes that muſt be uſed to obtaine reliefe againſt the ſaid tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Uſurpers; and for reducing the Parliament to its due Rights, Power and Priviledges, in the preſervation of the Kingdomes Lawes and Liberties.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>I. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 3.12, 13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Children are extortioners of my People, and women have rule over them: O my People, they that lead thee, cauſe thee to erre, and deſtroy the way of thy paths.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſhall enter into judgement with the Ancients of his People, and the Princes thereof: for ye have eaten up the Vineyard, the ſpoile of the poore is in your Houſes.</p>
               <p>What have ye to doe that ye beat my people to pieces, and grind the faces of the poore, ſaith the Lord, even the Lord of Hoſts?</p>
               <p>Woe be to the wicked, it ſhall be evill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed and Publiſhed for the information, advice, and benefit of the poore, oppreſſed, betrayed, and almoſt deſtroyed Commons of <hi>England.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:61874:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61874:2"/>
            <head>PLAINE TRVTH Without Feare, or Flattery.</head>
            <p>IN the 28 Pſalm, Verſe 6. The Spirit of God ſpeaking there of Iudges and Rulers, ſaith, they are Gods, and all of them children of the moſt high; but he telleth them they ſhall die like men, and fall as one of the Princes. We unhappy men of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> have at this time a generation of ambitious imperious men, ſome of both Houſes of Parliament, whoſe Names ye may elſewhere find; who by their power and ſubtill practiſes doe frame and aſſume to themſelves a ſupreame power over us, and would faine be taken for Gods, and Sons of the moſt High by us; yet they neither rule us like Gods, nor demean themſelves amongſt us as children of the moſt High: but rule us like Tyrants (a degenerate kind which God never made nor owned) and demean themſelves more like children of diſobedience (ſerving their own baſe luſts and pleaſures) then children of the moſt high: for were they ſuch, they would ſeeke the will of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heaven and good of his People. But the Spirit ſaith they ſhall die like men; the which it may be doubted theſe men beleeve not; but rather with the Atheiſticall Epicure thinke they ſhall dye like Beaſts, and that the ſoule, as well as the body returnes to the <hi>(pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam materiam,)</hi> and ſo, if they can but eſcape the hand of juſtice here, they dreame not of hearing of their wicked deeds hereafter; and therefore they have reſolved (it appeares) for the accompliſhment of their own unrighteous ends, after the manner of all Atheiſticall Stateſmen, who caſt the feare of God, and conſideration of death and judgement behind them) to aſſay all waies and meanes of wickedneſſe, as to vow and not pay, to promiſe and not performe, ſwear and forſweare, covenant and breake, to feign, flatter, and play the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, (I had almoſt ſaid the devill) to betray, deſtroy, rob, ſpoyle oppreſſe, and violate all law and rule of government, infringe all rights, and liberties, impriſon, perſecute, deceive their truſt, requite evill for good, and doe all manner of miſchiefe and injuſtice, even what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Sathan, and their wicked hearts ſhall prompt them unto; inſomuch that whatſoever they ſay or make ſhew of, their evill doings declare that they beleeve not an immortallity and judgement: they profeſſe themſelves Chriſtians, but if ye obſerve and conſider their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, you muſt ſay (and if you were a ſtranger you would ſweare) they were heathens: yea they doe worſe then heathens; for did ever heathens take the name of their inſenſible Gods of wood and ſtone, ſo frequently and ſolemnly into their mouthes, by way of oath and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as theſe men have done, and had it ſo little in reverence, and ſo little reſpect to what they have ſworne; as theſe men have had the name of the great and terrible God of heaven, and of their oathes made unto him? read all Stories, and ſearch all Centuries of Ages, and if there be any ſuch example of perjury, and ſwearing falſely by their God, equivalent to the example of theſe men of this generation, I will freely offer my ſelfe for a ſacrifice, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate my offence againſt their holines: and yet they are ready with <hi>Agurs</hi> Harlot, Pro. 30.20. to wipe their mouthes, and ſay we have done no wickednes. But that the truth may be made apparent, and expiated, let us heare their promiſes, vowes and ſpeeches, and compare their deeds and promiſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt they doe in the Proteſtation promiſe, vow, and proteſt, in the preſence of Almighty God (whom ſure they think is like the God of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, that could neither hear nor ſee) to maintaine and defend with their lives, powers, and eſtates, the true reformed Proteſtant Religion expreſſed in the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt all Popery, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Innovations within this Realme, contrary to the ſame doctrine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet they are now ſetting up, and have ſet up ſo farre as in them lyeth, a Religion never before heard of within this Realme, and quite contrary to the profeſſed doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it being wholly oppoſite unto Chriſt, and a meer Popiſh innovation, brought out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and violently impoſed upon us: And thus it comes to paſſe, by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61874:3"/>confederacy of a haughty trayterous Party in the houſe of Parliament, of which are the Earles of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and <hi>Stamford,</hi> Sir <hi>Phillip Stapleton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and others with the proud covetous Prieſts, for the advancement of their deſigne of uſurpation and Lordlines, both over his Majeſty and us, vow and proteſt in like manner, to maintaine and defend the Kings Royall Perſon, honour and eſtate, and the lawfull rights and liberties of the Subject, and every one that ſhould make the ſaid Proteſtation, in purſuance of the ſame; and that they will not for hope, feare, or other reſpect, relinquiſh this promiſe, vow, and proteſtation. And do they not accordingly maintain and defend the Kings Royall Perſon, Honour, and Eſtate? His Perſon with a company of Commiſſioners of their own ſtamp and temper, and with a Guard of able Horſemen and Souldiers (debauched <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his Regiment) as if they were afraid to intruſt any of the honeſt Commanders about him) as if he were rather a Prince of Theeves, then a Prince of three Kingdomes or of a free people? and his honour and eſtate they defend with all the power and might they can; taking the Supreame power upon themſelves to grant Pardons, ſell the Lands purchaſed with the lives and money of the People, without the Peoples conſent; make Judges, create Lord Keepers or Chancellours, (and yet the King in preſence, for they cannot now pretend a neceſſity by his abſence) and making uſe of his name to violate all Law; oppreſſe the People; and to commit all injuſtices in a word, to deſtroy our Liberties, and to execute their own Arbitrary wills. They ſpeake of having the Kings power with them virtually; but we can neither ſee nor find any of its proper vertue either among them, or from them; for his Majeſtres Regall power is juſt and mercifull, regulated by Law, preſervative and corrective; and not unjuſt, cruell, irregular, and illegall, deſacing and deſtructive; as the effects have been of the power which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath exerciſed. And concerning the Kings eſtate and revenues; no queſtion but it is accumulated and that they have it in bank, for they have been very parcimonious Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards; they can hardly ſpare either the maſter money for his neceſſities, or his ſervants any for wages: He, like a Ward, or Pupill, is at their ſet allowance, and content with the pittance his late tutors and guardians will allow him; I doubt not but it will prove that ſome of them have made better allowance to themſelves both out of his eſtate, and the Republiques alſo.</p>
            <p>Second, how by reaſon of the predominancy and power of this tyrannous Party, in both Houſes, whoſe malignant pernitious influence hath been, and ſtill is diffuſive throughout all the Parliaments actions; all theſe which have taken this Vew and Proteſtation, are and have been defended in purſuance of the ſame, it is ſufficiently manifeſt: For who but they that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to maintain the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, according to the doctrine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the power and purity of it, are hated, illegally proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and perſecuted, vilifyed, and reviled, and he is moſt favoured, and ſooneſt preferred, that can ſhew himſelfe moſt virulent, and violent againſt them? And if you do but sken, or looke (like a Hare) on the one ſide, at the Kings Crown and Dignity; you preſently incurre (through the powerful Votes of this Party) the Parliaments high diſlike and diſpleaſure, and it is a ſufficient badge, that you are an enemy, becauſe you are ſo to Traitors to the State) witnes the high diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the Armies wiſe, and juſt demand, of his Majeſties royall aſſent to an Act of indempnity, &amp; truly if they take a bare Parliament ordinance without the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſent, I will not give them one farthing for their ſecurity; and it will be found that their Iudges, Chancellours, Exciſe men, and Sequeſtrators, are in the ſame caſe as the Souldiers; And to endeavour or petition for liberty, according to the Proteſtation, is as much as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eg a Priſon, to ſue for juſtice, is to be accounted ſeditious; in a word, to be ſincere and honeſt, is to be adjudged worthy of no truſt, imployment, or preferment.</p>
            <p>But to make the truth, and the wicked practices and purpoſes of this deſtroying Party in both Houſes, yet more plain and open, theſe cunning contrivers, of our intended Vaſſalage and thraldom, frame a combination and confederacy by covenant with the Scots, and by power and ſubtilty ſurprize and enſnare therein the whole Parliament and Kingdom: (the which I pray read, and obſerve) In their feigned profeſſion of ſorrow they acknowledge, that their not prizing the Goſpell, nor labouring to receive Chriſt into their hearts, (and they ſay truly) hath been the cauſe of all other ſinnes amongſt us: And therefore with their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61874:3"/>hands liſted up to the moſt high God, they do ſolemnly ſwear ſincerely to endeavour a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of religion in the three Kingdomes, in doctrine, worſhip, diſcipline, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches: now what meanes this juggle, and to the example of the beſt reformed Churches? above they ſwear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and endeavour a reformation, and what ſincerity is here, to make mens impure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions equivalent to the infallible rule of Gods word? to make <hi>(dogma Presbyteri)</hi> the opinion of the Prieſt, adaequate to the unalterable laſt Will and Teſtament of Jeſus Chriſt? only here by this F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſt, theſe deceitfull Spirits endeavour to bring in ſomething of their own, that with their claw-back Prieſts they may ſeem to have ſomething to do with Chriſt in his Church government, and to ſit checke by joule with him in his throne: and thus they do ſtill diſ-eſteem the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpell, and oppoſe it in the power and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it; even as their Fathers did, ſo do they, harden their hearts againſt the Lord. If the word of God be a ſufficient rule to reform and govern the Church by; what need then of any other pattern or platforme? The beſt reformed Churches which are this day in Europe need reformation, yea the pure Church of Scotland, notwithſtanding all their pretence.</p>
            <p>For if you obſerve our Brethrens various double dealings, turnings and windings, ſelf ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and advantage-making in every buſineſſe they tranſact or negotiate with us, far unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming men pretending ſo great conſcientiouſnes in all things, &amp; ſo highly profeſſing the power of Religion, in purenes of life and converſation. At firſt they were againſt the King; then while he was with them, they ſpek and write highly for him, and now they have made the moſt they can of him,<note place="margin">The Scots have made more of the King, then Judas did of the King of heaven.</note> they are again become adverſaries to him; one while they preſs one part of their deceitfull Covenant; as at firſt they did that part, for bringing evill inſtruments unto condign pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, whilſt that Delinquents troubled them: Afterward, where by craft they had gotten the King among them, hoping thereby to have had him eſtabliſhed their Presbyterian Church-government within this Kingdom, they were very zealous for that part of the Covenant which concerns the preſervation and defence of his Majeſties perſon and authority: Now both the former are forgotten and they are at this inſtant extreme urgent, and importune for that part of the Covenant which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the reformation of Religion in the three Kingdomes: in dextrine, worſhip, diſcipline and government, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches: by which words, (the example of &amp;c.) they would have it granted that their Kirke of Scotland is the beſt reformed in all the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and therefore we are bound by this clauſe of the Covenant (they conceive) to reforme by their pattern; and to make their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment our example; as if they (blind Beetles) had obtained the very <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mum grad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> of the government of the Church of Chriſt comprehended in the Goſpel: thus uſing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant as a Waterman doth his Saile, to turn every way, and hereby they juſtify the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which ſaith, <hi>a double minded manty unſtable in all his wayes, Iam.</hi> 1. 8. but not one Word do they ſpeak for juſtice, or liberty of the Subject, though they ſee all oppreſſion and violence rage and raign amongſt us, this part of the Covenant they lifted up their hands as high to God, and ſwore as ſolemnly to performe, as any other, but becauſe they have no uſe for it, they regard it not: the truth is, they profeſs they know God, but in works they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him, being abhominable, and diſobedient, and to every good work reprobate.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak more particularly of our own Presbyterian Reformers, the Scotiſts of our Kindome M. <hi>Hollis, Stapleton,</hi> and the reſt of the zealous hypocrites, (with their Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prieſts) Covenanters, they ſware you ſee my Friends to endeavour a reformation in Religion according to the word of God, and the Parliament as ſeeming to adhere only to this ſure and alone neceſſary and ſufficient rule for reformation, and not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> take the bare opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of men for granted truths, without juſtification from the word of God, to which end they long ſince propounded queries concerning the ſaid government, for the Aſſembly to prove by the word of God, for the juſtification of it: the which queries I have here inſerted, for every mans better information, and conſideration, to wit:</p>
            <p>Firſt whether the Parochiall, and Congregationall Elderſhips, appointed by Ordinance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61874:4"/>of Parliament are <hi>jure divino,</hi> by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether all the members of the ſaid Elderſhip, are members thereof, or which of them are, <hi>jure divino,</hi> and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether the ſupreme Aſſemblies, or Elderſhips <hi>viz.</hi> the Claſſicall, Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and nationall, whether all, or any of them, or which of them, are <hi>jure divino,</hi> and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whether appeales from congregationall Elderſhips, to the Claſſicall Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, and Nationall Aſſemblies, or to any of them, are <hi>jure divino,</hi> and by the will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Whether Oecumenicall Aſſemblies, are <hi>jure divino,</hi> and whether there be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales from any of the former Aſſemblies to the ſaid Oecumenicall Aſſemblies, <hi>jure divino,</hi> by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Whether by the word of God, the power of judging and declaring what are noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſcandalous offences, and of conventing before them, triall, and actuall ſuſpending from the Sacrament ſuch offenders accordingly, either in the congregationall Elderſhip, or Presbytery, or in any other Elderſhip, or Presbytery preſented to the Houſes, as the advice of the aſſembly, and whether ſuch powers are in them only, or any of them, and in which of them <hi>jure divino,</hi> and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Whether there be any certaine and particular rules expreſſed in the word of God, to direct the ſaid Elderſhips or Presbyteries, or any of them in the exerciſe and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the powers aforeſaid, and which are thoſe rules?</p>
            <p>Eightly, is there any thing contained in the word of God, that the Supreme Magiſtrate in a Chriſtian State may not judge and determine what are the aforeſaid notorious &amp; ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous offences, and the manner of ſuſpenſion from the ſame, and in what particulars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the premiſes, are the ſaid Supreme Magiſtracy in the word of God excluded?</p>
            <p>In anſwer of which particulars, the Houſe of Commons deſired of the Aſſembly of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (falſly ſo callen) their proofs from Scripture, and to ſet down the ſeverall texts of Scripture in the expreſs words of the ſame. And it was alſo ordered that every particular Miniſter of the ſaid Aſſembly, that was, or ſhould be preſent at the debate of any of theſe Queſtions, ſhould upon every reſolution that was to be preſented to the Houſe concerning the ſame, ſubſcribe his reſpective name, either with the affirmative or negative, as hee ſhould give his vote, and that they which ſhould diſſent from the major part, ſhould ſet down their poſitive opinions, with the expreſſe texts of Scriptures upon which their opinions were grounded.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee an excellent way for the proofe of this Scottiſh creature preſcribed, and a great deal of ſeeming care in the Parliament to ſet up a Religion according to the word of God, and not according to the Church of Scotland: and yet though theſe ſeverall queries or queſtions were by the fallacious Aſſembly never anſwered unto this day, nor are they able to anſwer them ſatisfactorily, for they can neither immediate, or mediate, directly, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, prove by the word of God, and Goſpell of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, their ſo much pres'd Presbyterian government to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> by divine Law or right, as they moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, &amp; audaciouſly have alledged: yet nevertheleſs although theſe queries were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſolved, nor the Parliament ever ſatisfied by ſufficient proofe out of the word of God, of the lawfulneſs of this government, whether it be the government of Jeſus Chriſt or not, hath this evill party (where of Mr <hi>Hollis</hi> a man ever factious, is reputed chiefe) by their heady preſumptuous courſes, to raiſe to themſelves a faction from London &amp; the Scots, for their owne ſecurity, and to drive on their own premeditated deſign of dominion and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity, prevailed to have it eſtabliſhed by Ordinance, enjoyning it in all places, and upon all perſons, with as much rigour and ſeverity as ever the Biſhops did their conformity, all which (ye ſee) is directly againſt their Covenant, and no other then plain perjury: but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they can eſtabliſh this Scottiſh Presbyterian government, they can never abſolutely eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh tyranny, for the expedients of this Presbyterian government conduce directly unto ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, even to aboliſh all rules of Law and civil liberty, it is an antipathy to Monarchy, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61874:4"/>the legall power of civill Magiſtracy and brings under a yoake (where it is predominant) both King and People (as ſhall God willing be demonſtrated fully in due time) and by this meanes theſe aſpirers hope through the help of the Preiſts to order King <hi>Charles</hi> (as the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians in Scotland did King <hi>James</hi>) whom they did reſtraine, affront, diſobey, and raiſe tumults againſt) if he prove refractory to any of their arbitrary Councels; and ſo ſuppreſſe and curb us the free Commoners that we ſhall not be able either to help him, or remedy our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Yet queſtionleſs, if ye aske any of theſe our maſter Reformers, if when they made and took the Covenant, they did not intend to make Gods word their direct rule of reformation? They will anſwer, yes: otherwiſe they muſt confeſs themſelves moſt hatefull hypocrites; denying the truth and ſufficiency of the holy Scriptures, men that intend no Religion, but a treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſigne againſt King and People under that notion, and I wiſh it doe not prove ſo in the end by ſome men. If they did intend (as they will not deny) to make Gods word their Rule, to reforme by: why doe they make the Church of Scotland, the rule of their Reformation, and caſt the word of God behinde them? Why do they enforce upon us the reformation (or rather deformation) of another Kingdom, no waies juſtified or approved by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not endeavour (as they have ſworne) ſincerely, to ſeeke out what the good will of the Lord is, concerning his Church, and worſhip, what order and rule he hath preſcribed and left us by his owne Son in the Goſpel? Doth not God the Father ſay, <hi>This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son</hi> heare <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hin,</hi> Mark. 9.7. And is it not written, And <hi>Moſes</hi> truely ſaid unto the Fathers, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, him ſhall ye heare in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you,<note n="*" place="margin">not the Scots, nor the Prieſts.</note> and it ſhall come to paſs, that every ſoule which ſhall not heare that Prophet ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people,<note n="*" place="margin">marke &amp; tremble all yee Prieſts &amp; Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 22, 23. And doubtleſs, Chriſt, who was a Son, was not leſs faithfull in Gods houſe then <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was a ſervant. And againe ye have a ſure word (ſaith the Apoſtle) unto which yee doe well to take heed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. Yet doe theſe preſumptuous men deſpiſe this command of God, and neglect this ſure word; hearken to their owne corrupt humours, take heed to their owne ambitious covetons deſires, and ſo proceed in deſpight of God and his Chriſt, to erect a government after their owne inventions: But they will tell you that the Aſſembly have fearched the Scriptures, and had reſpect to the word, in framing this government, I beleeve they have, but as the Devill did, to make uſe of them for his own ends, againſt Chriſt; for they did not ſearch to find what government it was the Goſpell did hold out and warrant, and propound and promote that: But they firſt reſolve upon &amp; propound ſuch a government as will ſerve their purpoſe, and then they apply themſelves to make it good by Scriptures, or to enforce the Scriptures for a warrant: thus have they made their forme of Church government the rule of Gods word, and not Gods word a rule to their form of government, having done no otherwiſe then many Attu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nies &amp; Clerks doe, who often draw Declarations and writings by another mans preſident or pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, without examining or conſulting the Law, in the caſe; which is juſt as if a Taylor ſhould firſt make a ſuit, and then make uſe of his meaſure. And grant that this Presbyteriall government be according to the word of God, it is ſo <hi>(in toto)</hi> Is it ſo abſolute that there is no degree of Reformation above it? if ſo, then the <hi>Scots</hi> have exceeded that grand planter of Churches, Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> for he told the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> That he would yet ſhew them a more excellent way, <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 31. And that we know but in part, and prophecie but in part, but when that which is perfect is come, that which is imperfect ſhall be aboliſht, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and the Prophets ſpake of a new heaven and a new earth, wherein dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth righteouſneſs. Of ſuch a beautifull &amp; perfect Reformation and change, as if it was a new world, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. and <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.17. I hope no proud Prieſt or Presbyterian, dare affirme that there is yet any ſuch Reformation or change in <hi>Scotland;</hi> righteouſneſs dwelleth not there I am ſure: and I would it was not almoſt baniſhed out of <hi>England.</hi> For as much then as there is a reformation more true and excellent than theirs (or elſe theirs is none at all) why may not the Independents (ſo called) or ſome others, approach neerer to it then they? with-waies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61874:5"/>then doth in the waies of the Presbyterians: unleſſe the Presbyterians will affirme themſelves the onely wiſe, and that the ſpirit of the moſt high God, dwels only in them: but then they muſt give me leave to aske them Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> queſtion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.36. <hi>Came the word of God out from you? Or came it unto you onely?</hi> Or did the Biſhop ſeale unto the Presbyterian Prieſts the holy Spirit, when they ſealed unto them their Ordination, and ſo they have kept it ever ſince cloſe up in a box, to be brought forth in theſe times? Truly (my friends) as learned Rabbies as they are, <hi>They erre, not knowing the Scriptures: To the Law</hi> (therefore) <hi>and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them: Iſa.</hi> 8.20. The Devill preached truer doctrine, when he ſaid, <hi>that Jeſus was the Sonne of God, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> 8.29. then theſe Prieſts when they ſay that the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an government is <hi>jus divinum,</hi> the law and government of Jeſus Chriſt; but this is as true as that the Church of Rome is a true Church; the which they do now<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Seymour</hi> one of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly affirmes it in a diſpute.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, to prove their Antichriſtian ſtanding true. And now here by the way I will occaſionally put a few Queries.</p>
            <p>Firſt whether in caſe a forme of Church-government and worſhip, contrary to the word of God, be by force put upon us, againſt our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, by the Parliament and Presbyterian Aſſembly: it be not by the ſame reaſon, as lawfull for us to refuſe and reſiſt it <hi>(vi et armis)</hi> by force<note n="*" place="margin">And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe it is inforced by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation and without the Kings approbation.</note>as it was for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cots in like manner, to reject and reſiſt the forme of Church-government, and worſhip put violently upon them againſt their conſciences by the King and Biſhops?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether the <hi>Scots</hi> ought, or have any more authority or right to preſcribe or endeavour an impoſition of Church-government, and worſhip upon the people of <hi>England,</hi> then the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have to preſcribe and endeavour the impoſition of the like upon the People of <hi>Scotland?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, If not: Whether the <hi>Scott</hi> go not beyond their Laſt? Do not move out of their ſphere, and intermeddle with what they ought not?</p>
            <p>And now ſeeing, there is, (as cannot be denyed) a more high pitch of Reformation in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and holy worſhip, then is yet attained, or diſcovered; I hope it is no offence nor tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion againſt the State, for any true Chriſtian, or ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, to preſs hard af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and not to conform himſelf to fixed formes, bounds &amp; limits, thereby to confine Gods holy Spirit: Ye ſtiffe-necked and rebellious (Prieſts) of uncircumciſed hearts and eares, ye have alwaies reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt; as your Fathers (the Biſhops) did, ſo do yee. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. I have inſiſted the more upon this particular that the truth herein might be cleare; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great deluſion put upon the People by many of our pretending Reformers, through their grand Oaths and pretexts, of expelling all Popery and Popiſh innovations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven whatſoever ſhould be contrary to ſound doctrine (for ſo I underſtand thoſe words in the Proteſtation, contrary to the ſame doctrine) and to reforme Religion according to the Word of God, and to eſtabliſh it in the power and purity of it, and yet notwithſtanding apply all their intereſt and power to ſupport an<note n="*" place="margin">If the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops were anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, what is theirs who ſtand by their ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and power?</note> anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Miniſtery, and to eſtabliſh Church-government, whoſe fruits and effects are nothing but impiety, and hypocriſie, a Reli on which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts more in outward formes and rites, after the manner of <hi>Moſes;</hi> then in power and piety according to the Goſpel: which conduceth (as appears) more to tyranny, then Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And ſo I will pretermit their Vowes and Oaths, and come to ſome of their ſpeeches and ſayings: and here I will ſhew you another truth, by the diſcovery of another falſhood, and treacherous vanting act, of the ſame traiterous party or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which ſerves as a patterne, repreſentation, or image, of the forme of the yoake of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which (it may be ſuſpected) they ſtudy, and intond to put upon all the Counties and Corporations in the Kingdome, and by which, with the helpe of their determined new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Horſe (it is probable) they purpoſe if they can, to ſubjugate the whole Land, and to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61874:5"/>conſorme the People to their arbitrary wills, even to pay, and bease, doe, and ſuffer, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſhall thinke ſit to enjoyne them, or exact upon them, as well in reſpect of things ſpirituall as civill. In the Parliaments Remonſtrance of the 2 of November, 1642. Book Decl. pag. 700. they tell us, That all Rights or Intereſt of publicke truſt, are only for the publicke good, and not for private advantages, nor to the prejudice of any mans particular intereſt, much lefle of the publique. And in May 1642. Book Decla. 172. They call God to witneſſe, that the ſafetie of the Kingdome, and peace of the people, is their onely aime; and becauſe the King would not believe them therein (and well had it been for us if we bad ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo done) nor truſt them wholly therewith, great grew the conteſtation (as yee may well remember) betweene the King and the Parliament, about the ſetling of the Militia of the Kingdome, and indeed it was one unhappy cauſe of the quarrell between them: The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament then pretending that the King ought not to lettle it without them, that it behoved them to have the nomination of ſuch perſons as were to be intruſted therewith, in whom they might conſide: the King affirmes (and they afterwards grant) That the whole power thereof was intruſted by Law in him, for the preſervation and defence of the Kingdom; yet becauſe the King would not paſſe the Ordinance in Febu. 1641. for the ſetling it in ſuch forme as they deſired, though the perſons they nominated were not refuſed; they preſently proteſt (I with they were as quick to doe juſtice, as they are to take exceptions) to diſpoſe of it without him, and accordingly reſolve. <hi>(Rebus ſit ſtantibus, &amp; nolenti Regi)</hi> that is, they expreſſe, in extream diſtraction, when ſorreigne forces are probably invited and a malignant Pepiſh paritie offended, &amp;c. the ordering it to be in them for the (obſerve) preſervation of the Republicke, and to prevent the turning the Armes of the Kingdome upon it ſelfe, ſee the Parliaments anſwer to their owne queſtion, pag. 150. of the Booke of Decla. But I hope the caſe is now altered, for although our diſtractions be ſtill continued by the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Councell, of a pernicious ſactions partie in both Houſes (the heads of which were, and are the cauſe both of thoſe diſtractions and theſe, who like katchers of Eeles, love to fiſh in the troubled waters) here is now no ſeare of invited forreign forces, and as for that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Popiſh partie then ſo much condemned, it is utterly ſubdued and ſuppreſſed, and therefore in all reaſon <hi>(Rebus nunc ſic ſtantibus)</hi> that is) the ſo much feared publicke ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary being long ſince conquered, all viſible danger removed, and the King recovered out of the hands of evill Counſellors, and at preſent with themſelves, and not legally diveſted of his Regall power and right of truſt; in a word, all juſt pretext, and colour of extremity being taken away, they take too much upon them, and abuſe both King and People, who in this opportunitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Royall Aſſent may be had, doe diſpoſe of the Militia without him, neither requiting his conſent therein, nor admitting the People according to the Law, to the Election of (a thing the King allowed them) the perſons who are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, with the dispoſe and command of their ſtrength and armes, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eſtates, liberties and lives: I am certaine, in caſe (as God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bid) the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Throne ſhould by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome vold, the Parliaments are not their owne Meſters, nor can by the fundamentall Law and conſtitution of this Kingdome, diſpoſe of us the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England, and out power, armes, or intereſt, without our conſents, how much leſſe at this inſtans: All the Commons of England have more juſt ground of jealouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e from them in now ſo doing, and of complaint and accuſation againſt that malevolent ill-affected party among them, by whoſe power and influence it hath beene effected, conſidering the perſons unto whom the Militia and ſtrength of the Kingdome, is in divers places of late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, then the Parliament ever had from and againſt the King, for refuſing onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in their way and manner: for they choſe the perſons, and he approved them; but the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are herein both chooſers and approvers (as in many things, many of them are both Judge and Witneſſe) though we neither approve, nor aſſent; and thus wee, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the King, are in this particular debarred from them, of our right and priviledge: but this is not the greateſt detriment we ſuſtaine, and are likely without prevention to ſuffer, and which this predominant malicious partie intends, hereby: for doe but caſt your eye, and ſee and conſider what perſons are put out of the Militia; and what perſons are continued, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61874:6"/>and intruſted; and yee will preſently judge by a little what the whole meanes. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, firſt for for an introduction, the pretended Lord Maior, Aldermen, and Comon-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, muſt petition in the name of the Citie, though the Citie never propounded it to them, to have the Militia ſetled in their owne hands, (as they had formerly) and why not then to have it by their Charter, but by Ordinance for a certaine time? and this by the power and prevalency of the malevolent partie is forthwith obtained, becauſe it tends to their predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, tyrannous ends: approved Alderman <hi>Pennington,</hi> who ſtood in the breach when they all were afraid, whoſe ſidelitie and abilitie was throughly experimented, at ſuch time when as the winds blew higheſt, and the ſtormes grew ſtrongeſt; a man adjudged by the Citie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be their Parliament-man, and by the Parliament worthy to be Lieutenant of the Tower of London, is now no longer worthy to be intruſted with the Militia, but turned out as a man ſuſpected; ſo are the Aldermen, <hi>K. Foulk, Weaver,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Col. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> though a Member of the Houſe, alſo Col. <hi>Player, Tichburn,</hi> and others: And why? they are not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute for the Faction; they were oppoſite to <hi>Bunce,</hi> and <hi>Bellamy,</hi> the Court of Aldermen and Common-Councell, in the proſecution of the laſt indirect, illegall, and factious Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of Presbytery, and therefore they are not any longer to be conſided in, or ſit to have the command of any power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſoever they had a parcell of dry thanks from the Houſe for their former fidelitie and paines: it is better I confeſſe then a Priſon (as <hi>Lilburn, Tuleday, Robinſon, Nichols,</hi> &amp; multitudes more have had) for their good ſervice. Yet I muſt tell them, it is but after the old manner of the Court, who uſed to put a man off with an hypocriticall complement, when they had no further occaſion to uſe him, or were deſirous to be quit of him: and it is obſerved, that empty thanks is a ſufficient reward from the Houſe, for any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, though his ſervice hath been never ſo good, and ſuperlative, unleſſe they have ſome other deſign or ingagement upon him: but to Knaves and Fooles they have been very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and free, (witnes the 10 l. given to the two Officers that brought up Enſigne <hi>Nichols;</hi> and the arrears lately ordered to be paid two great ones, for diſcovering two great lyes: by which you may ſee, they can pay whom they liſt, and whom they liſt they will not:) I could inſtance you ſome examples of late, and their owne neſts are generally ſo well feathered, that many, or moſt of them are almoſt ſmothered, they can neither ſee, hear nor ſpeake. Alas poore Commons of England, your backs in the meane time are left bare and naked! But to proceed; marke what honeſt men are continued, put in, and intruſted with the Militia, for the honeſt men that are put out and diſtruſted: Aldermen, <hi>Bunce, Adams, Langham,</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man of knowledge can read them) Colonels, <hi>Weſt,</hi> and <hi>Bellamy,</hi> the one an oppreſſive Goaler, the other an arrogant Mag-pye, and <hi>Bromfield</hi> that ran away at Newberry: the Lord Maior Sir <hi>John Geere,</hi> who was plundered for his 20th. and 5th. part, who maliciouſly cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvents men, that he may like the devill take them in a ſnare, and then impriſons them, contrary to law, (as he did Maſter <hi>Tew,</hi> and then ſent his Marſhall to apprehend him without a Warrant) a hopefull Magiſtrate, and ſit to be intruſted with the publique Sword, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the Lawes, and defence of the Subjects juſt Rights and Liberties: and that Sir <hi>John Woolaſton,</hi> who by the Law is more worthy to be arraigned before a Bench of Aſſize for buying ſtoln<note n="*" place="margin">It is truth, and when time ſerves will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> Plate of the Kings, then to ſit upon the Bench of judgement to oppreſſe and doe juſtice, as his common practice is, or to be intruſted with the Militia; for it is contrary to all principles of reaſon, that a Magiſtrate, or publique Miniſter, who is unjuſt to the People in his place or practiſe, will ever be faithfull to them in time of trouble or diſtreſſe, or defend either them or their liberties, whenſoever they are aſlayled; the Hawke will as ſoone defend the Dove, and the Kite the Chickens: this is that Sir <hi>John Woolaſton,</hi> who right or wrong commits all to Newgate that come before him, for the benefit of his brother the head Goaler there; who is as diligent to ſtarve and deſtroy them when he hath them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cuſtody, (as he he did one <hi>Sparks</hi> lately, and hath done many more) as the other is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them. As for Alderman <hi>Gibs</hi> of the Militia, he hath a good ſtock of money in the name of his Sonne, beyond the Seas, he need not care which way the world goes; good Sir <hi>John
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61874:6"/>Woolaſton</hi> and he, had their fingers both in one Pye; I hope they lick'd them cleane, and themſelves (like Bullocks) ſat, though they have lick't others leane; their ſilver tongues ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit them well in <hi>Rylees</hi> buſineſſe, and they have you know been eſteemed honeſt and truſty ever ſince: I could read you a Character of moſt of them, but to avoid prolixitie I will now forbeare till a more convenient time: and will only tell you what I apprehend to be the end of this ſudden, and ſo happy ſettlement of the Militia of London; the effect, and what you may expect by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this meanes, the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis, Stapleton,</hi> Earl Senior, and the reſt of this trayterous faction, who have occaſioned the violation of all our Lawes and Liberties, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed their truſt; and are the chiefe obſtructers of the course of Juſtice, and redreſſe of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, promoters of all evill councels, and the cauſe of the continuance of all our troubles and diſtractions; who among other things drive a deſign to ſave their own Stakes, and ſecure their own lives; for that they know they are for theſe things lyable to queſtion, and abnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Juſtice, doe conceive they have well ſecured themſelves from all invaſion, by Petition or cry for juſtice againſt them, from any partie within the City.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they ſhall by this meanes the more eaſily erect their new formed Monſter of Presbytery; for what they cannot perſwade, they will inforce, and who (thinke they) now dare, or can reſiſt it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. They conceive they ſhall eaſily ſuppreſſe the Independent partie (as they terme them) and div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt them fróm petitioning for Law and Libertie, to both which theſe vile men are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together averſe; and that if they doe notwithſtanding, continue ſuch their petitioning, yet may they the more ſecurely deny and diſtaſte their petitions, and puniſh their perſons: for is not the Militia in their hands? And if they will not ſubmit like ſlaves, but begin to ſtirre and ſtruggle; then the Militia is ready to oppoſe them as Rebels and Traytors, although they challenge but right and juſtice of their ſervants, who are many of them become Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: and this is apparent by their late declaring their high diſpleaſure againſt that juſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, &amp; the Petitioners, for divers points of liberty &amp; juſtice, which was preferred by a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of wel-affected Citizens: firſt, it was intercepted &amp; anticipated, contrary to the courſe of Parliaments, and the libertie of the Subject, by the meanes of Recorder <hi>Glin,</hi> (who hath ſhewed more favour to Captaine<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully killed a man, and being brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder, he baſely reviled the poore widow, and freed the murtherer.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas Evans,</hi> a notorious murderer, then ever he did to poore Orphans, for whom he ſhould have been a juſt Advocate) witneſſe the Orphans of M. <hi>Bury,</hi> againſt whom he tooke Fees (if not bribes) by which meanes (notwithſtanding many petitions, and as many faire promiſes from the then temporzing Lord Major <hi>Adams,</hi> and others of that Orphan de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Faction) the ſaid Orphans to this day can obtaine no juſtice, nor part of their fathers perſonal eſtate, unleſſe they will take fourſcore for four hundred pounds, &amp; thus are the poote Orphans miſerably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uin'd having ſpent the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of their annuall revenue for five yeares together, to obtaine juſtice, but by the corruption of <hi>Brigandine</hi> (who ſquares his actions by his Maſters Rule) and power of the Recorder who is the Executers friend, nothing can be done; all paſſages are block't up; honeſt men dare not ſpeak, and knaves will not, and ſo the poor Orphans are left altogether remedileſſe:) but to proceed, the aforeſaid Petition being referred to a Commmittee, and the Citizens put off with faire words, till this grand Ordinance for the Militia was paſſed, and then preſently they thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, as if the Petition had tended to the prejudice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urch and State.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If they want money, or a new Army to ſecure themſelves, that old Aſſe the Citie muſt raiſe men, or ſund out their Trained Bands for them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of London muſt pay and beare, or elſe be plundered, and what remedy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ever the Parliament will exact, and the Military men execute, the Commons of London muſt obey and ſubmit to, though never ſo unjuſt a tax, or impoſition: But you will ſay, the Trained Bands will not be all of a mind, but this Partie having prevailed to New-Modelling of the Commiſſioners, you ſhal ſee them New-Model the Train Bands alſo, &amp; here is the firſt piece of the frame of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſlavery; &amp; muſt ſerve (if they can carry it) for a leading caſe unto the whole Kingdom</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61874:7"/>
            <p>The effects (yee Commons of London) which yee may expect hence, are the utter abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of your free Elections of your Maior, Aldermen, Sheriffs, Common-Councell-men, and other publicke Officers, of your body and Corporation, ſo that now you may bid all your priviledges adue, and the free, borne Apprentices after ſeaven years hard ſervitude,<note n="*" place="margin">Marke yee Apprentices.</note> expect a Perpetuall vaſſalage; by this means the hopes yee had of the recovery of antient Rights and immunitie are fruſtrate, and yee (after all your coſts and adventures for your liberties) become the firſt abſolute ſlaves in England, if God doe not otherwiſe prevent, or raiſe up ſome <hi>Othniel, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hud, Shamger, Barak,</hi> or <hi>Gideon</hi> to deliver you. And in ſuch hands as theſe, this deſperate domineering faction, by ſymptomes and ſignes, purpoſe to ſettle the Militia, in all the Counties and Corporations of the Kingdom, and have already in Durham, Cumberland, and other places Northward, put it principally into their hands, who are declared Traytors and Enemies to the State, Malignant and Delinquents, ſome of which have been actually in war againſt the Parliament and their Country, as Sir <hi>George Vane,</hi> old Sir <hi>Henries</hi> Son, who was in armes with the King, and is now made one of the Deputie Lieutenants of the Militia for Durham, a Juſtice of Peace, and a Committee-man, and yet ſcarce good commoditie for the Hang-man, S. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> of Cumberland ſuch another, yet by the prevalency of this partie, intruſted with the <hi>poſſe-Commitatus,</hi> whereby he may raiſe the Countie, and cut all honeſt mens throats, if he imagine cauſe: To tell you of the commands &amp; power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Lieutenant Col. <hi>Offcere,</hi> Cap. <hi>Muſgrave, Story, Stoddert,</hi> and divers others are inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and intruſted in thoſe parts, who have beene in armes againſt the Parliament and their Country, to the great trouble, hazard, and affliction of all the faithfull &amp; wel-affected there, beſides many others in other places of the Land, would be too tedious; let theſe for preſent ſufflice for example: and all, rather then to truſt the honeſt and approved in the Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are contrary to their treaſonable deſignes and practices, and will not ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not the Country to become their vaſſalls and pack-horſes. I wiſh thoſe Northern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries had no juſt cauſe of complaint againſt that deceitfull double-dealing Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> I will for ſpeciall cauſe (not that I fear or regard him, or any man, farther then he is ſincere and vertuouſly honourable) ſpace ſpare him; but it it is good for him and others to repent, and doe their firſt workes, leſt a worſe thing befall them; there is nothing hid, but it may be made manifeſt: to runne away from a fight for feare, is tolle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able, and is contingent to the greateſt<note n="*" place="margin">Witnes Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Leſhley.</hi>
               </note> Generall, but for a profeſſed Souldier of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to turne his backe and flce from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, is to be abhorred. Hath not Chriſt ſaid, He wll be aſhamed of ſuch, when he ſhall come in his Fathers glory with the holy Angells? <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.38. And did <hi>Jehiſaphat</hi> proſper, that tooke part with <hi>Ahab?</hi> Or ever any eſcape by iniquitie? And if <hi>Meroz</hi> was curſed, yea, bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly curſed, becauſe they would not helpe, what are they that doe hurt? And are not they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo curſed (though they be doing) that doe Gods worke negligently? Conſider theſe things ſeriouſly all yee that are ſunke &amp; ſetled upon the lees, all the Neuters and indifferent ones, that plead moderation, non-ſeaſon, and prudence, for your baſeneſſe of ſpirit, negligence, and cowardice, in the great Chuſe of God, and this diſtreſſed Kingdom, and yee <hi>(Timedi)</hi> yee ſearfull ones, who are more afraid of the face and diſpleaſure of man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrels, and whoſe councels periſh, then of the power and wrath of God, Who is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, and whoſe councels abide for ever: That feare more the loſing of your places and profits, then the loſing of Gods favour and countenance, and the peace of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Read that 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> and tremble, remember your ſelves, rouſe up your ſpirits, and ſhew your ſelves couragious for truth and juſtice, and zealous for the glory of the Lord of Hoſts; if yee will not, know that deliverance will come to Gods People ſome other way, and yee ſhall not eſcape. As for M. <hi>Hollis</hi> and others, whoſe councells and practices tend princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to treaſon and tyranny, injuſtice and violence (I know what I ſay, and doubt not yet but in time to ſee it proved ſo) who live without Law, and act contrary to Law, like Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rebels: Let ſuch men know, that God will render unto them according to their workes; and I am confident, that they ſhall never be able to acompliſh their wicked enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61874:7"/>and that the pit they have digged for others, they ſhall fall into themſelves. God will take them by their own counſels, as he did in old time, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hitophell</hi> and <hi>Haman;</hi> and as hee did <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in theſe dayes: yea, in thoſe two preſidents, they have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a halter for their owne necks, and their owne words ſhall be their Judges: <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> were condemned for reaſoanble councells and ſpeeches. endeavours, and intentions of ſubverting the fundamentall lawes, and frame of government, and of ſetting up an arbitrary power, and rule of government: And whether <hi>Hollis</hi> and others, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous complices, have not been, (not only the intenders and indeavourers, but) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all authors and actours of theſe things, I doe appeale to all intelligent men, who have taken any cognizance of their councels and actions? So that if the King (as it is a queſtion) did want juſt matter of occaſion in his charge of treaſon againſt M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and others in 1641. both he and the whole Kingdome may without much ſearch, find enough doubt eſſe at this time; yes, have not M. <hi>Hollis</hi> and others, his complices and confederates, not onely verified many or moſt of thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Read &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them, and compare them with their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, B. Decla. page 34.</note> articles of Treaſon and miſdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors: but alſo argumented and exceeded them in many things? I could (but at preſent for ſpeciall reaſons will not) particularize: in the mean time, (my friends) make uſe of your owne obſervations, call your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories to account, and compare things with things, adviſe well, make your ſelves ſtrong, and feare not. Why ſhould the old Engliſh proverb (for our love and faithfulneſſe) be made true upon us? Save a traytor or theefe from the gallowes, and he ſhall be the firſt that ſhall hang you: indeed we are neer it, if we doe not beſtir our ſelves and prevent it: But it is better that a few preſumptuous men; whoſe Lucifer like pride and ambition hath lifted them up to Heaven, ſhould be caſt down into oblivion and darkneſſe, then the whole Nation periſh.</p>
            <p>And therefore yee free Commoners of England up quickly, and looke about you; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly the ſnare prepared for you, and compare the vehement endeavours of theſe trayterous perſons to disband the Army, (which hath tought and is reſolved to ſtand for your liberties) with this their patterne, and firſt piece of thraldome, in ſetling the Militia thus at this time in ſuch mens hands in London, and their putting power into the hands of ſuch as are enemies to the publicke in the Country, and ſee if theſe men intend any thing to you and yours but bondage and ſlavery, and this is part of that ye are told in the<note n="*" place="margin">Both worth your notice.</note> books called the Warnings for all the Counties of England, and the New found Stratagem upon the Petition of Eſſex. Be vigilant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and aſſiſtant to keep the Army on foot, for your owne defence, and preſervation of your ſelves, your eſtates and liberties, Country and poſterities, from inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable vaſſalage, and irrecoverable ruine; for that once downe, this ambitious party, who aime at Soveraignty, to make the King their ſcorne, and us their ſlaves, will preſently not only turne the Militia in every place upon the Country, (as they have already deſigned in the City) but raiſe horſe alſo after the manner of Germany, in all Counties of the Kingdome for the better ſecuring themſelves, and this their forme of tyranny, and if ſuch bee no traytors, who be? Where ſhall we find any and if this be to imploy their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke truſt, for the<note n="*" place="margin">Book Decla. page 700.</note> publicke good, and whether their<note n="†" place="margin">Page 172.</note> onely aime, bee herein the Kingdomes ſafety and the peoples peace, as they have declared and ſpoken, let all England judge? And thus yee ſee they falſify their words and Declarations, as well as break their Oaths &amp; Proteſtations: but in their Booke of Declarations page 207. they ſay, That in caſe of extreme danger, and his Majeſties refuſall to ſettle the Militia of the Kingdom, the Ordinance (that is the Ordinance which was then made in that time of ſuch extreme danger) agreed upon by both Houſes for the Militia, doth oblige the people, and ought to be obeyed by the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, but now, (bleſſed be God) here is no ſuch caſe of extreme danger, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the King been ſo much as petitioned, or ſought unto for this Ordinance of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of London, and therefore it doth not bind the People, nor can they by the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes of the Land, be compelled to obey it, beſides they ordering the Militia to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61874:8"/>publique hurt, and not to the publique good, contrary to the intent and equity of the Law, and the end o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their truſt, the people are <hi>ipſo facto)</hi> diſcharged of their obedience to their Ordinance, for we are not bound to obey to our own dammage and deſtruction; ſee this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by their owne deſtruction and argument, in Book of Decl. page 150. But to make a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovery of the truth, by diſcovering more of this evill parties falſhood, breach of truſt, and traitorous practices againſt us: take notice, that in the Book of Declarations pa. 720. the Parliament declare, That it is the liberty and priviledge of the people, to petition unto them, for the eaſe and redreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of their grievances and oppreſſions, and that they are (marke) bound in duty to receive their Petition: here is a fair acknowledgement; but I pray you marke their actions: many tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſand honeſt and really affected to the publick li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, in the City, had prepared a petition to have been preſented to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for redreſs of ſome grievances and oppreſſions, and reſtoration of ſome liberties and priviledges, comprehending nothing but things legall and juſt, what they ought to grant this Petition, contrary to all courſe of Parliament and the liberty of the Subject, was by the power and ſubtilty of the aforeſaid faction or party, (who have their ſetting dogs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles to diſcry and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt for them) intercepted (as thus they anticipated the Armies Petition) before it was perfected, and made ready to be preſented, the copy of it was read in the Houſe, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erred to a Committee (whereof fierce-ſiery M. <hi>Lee</hi> was Chair-man) to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and report it (they did not ſo by the factions Petition and Remonſtrance framed by the pretended Lord Maior and Common-Coucnell-men) againſt which they then not finding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny juſt cauſe of exception, held the vowchers thereof with faire words in hopes of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, untill they had mounted their late new Ordinance of the militia for London, and then they declared thir diſtaſte and diſpleaſure againſt it; the which in j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt dealing &amp; violation of our native liberty and priviledge, the petitioners not brooking, preſented a Petition to the Houſe of Commons for juſtice and redreſs, and deſire that their former Petition might not be cenſured before it was in due order preſented; hereupon, <hi>Hollis, Stapleton,</hi> and the reſt of that faction (traitours to their Country) according to their uſuall courſe through their malignant influence prevalency, procured this latter Petition to be voted ſeditious, and that both it and the former ſhould be burnt by the hands of the hang-man, (was there ever ſuch a thing done before by a Parliament in England, ſure not) and that to queſtion any act done in the Houſe, was a breach of the priviledges of Parliament: but by cunning to intercept the former Petition, and tyrannically to ſuppreſs and reject it, and illegally to impriſon ſome of the Petitioners for it (as they have done M. <hi>Tue,</hi> and M. <hi>Browne</hi>) was no breach of the priviledge of the ſubject (No, deare friends and fellow Commoners, unleſs ye have (like fooles) reſolved with your ſelves, after ſo ſharp and Hoody a conteſtation for your Law, and your liberties, to relinquiſh your claime by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the good old Law; and to hold your lives and liberties, and all you have, by the Arbitrary Votes of the Houſe of Commons, and to become Tenants at will, unto a company of Traitors, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants: up in Gods name, up, demand redreſſe, and vindicate your ſelves, and native rights, againſt Votes and Votesr, <hi>(hodie mihi, cras <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi> what theſe men doe, to this or that part, or place of the Kingdome, and people to day, thy may and will doe to another part or place to morrow. And they have injuſtly refuſed more then a few (as that of the Counties of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Hereford,</hi> and divers others from all parts) petitioners for redreſs of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and granting of libetties already, and in this late particular preſident, is the very effence and end of a Parliament perverted; the rights of Parliament, &amp; the ancient courſe of Parliamentary proceedings ſubverted, and our native rights and priviledges, ſo much as lies in this deſtructive party, wholly vacated and deſtroyed. And whether this ſtrainge Vote and fact, doe not juſtifie the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th article exhited by the King againſt <hi>Hollis</hi> and others 1641. (Book Decl. page 35.) by which he chargeth them, To have traiterouſly endeavoured, to ſubvert the very rights and beings of Parliaments<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I beſeech you all yee lovers of Englands liberties, conſider, and judge: And alſo part of that firſt ſeventh Article exhibited by the Houſe againſt the Earle of <hi>Strafford.</hi> Yea, conſider I beſeech you, compare and ſee, if the words, waies, councels and practices of the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter, Hollis, Stapleton</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61874:8"/>their complices and confederates, doe not fully anſwer the 1, 2. 5. and part of the 6. Article exhibited in 1641. by the King: and to the firſt, and part of the 2, 3, 4, 6, &amp; 7. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and ſome others (only <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mutan lis</hi>) which were exhibited by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons againſt <hi>Strafford,</hi> and alſo to ſome which were exhibited againſt <hi>Canterbury,</hi> even as face anſwereth to face, in water? Truly wee are no longer free, but abſolute ſlave already: if we may not petition for our libertyt, what? unleſſe we will firſt aske them what we ſhall petition, we muſt not it ſeems at all Petition? Away with ſuch Traitors from the Earth.</p>
            <p>This Act and Vote, anſwers thoſe traiterous ſpeeches of <hi>Harvy</hi> and <hi>Solloway,</hi> two cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt men of the Houſe of Commons, who impudently ſaid, (note) That the Parliament might doe what they would, and were not to be queſtioned for it. One of the Articles of high treaſon charged upon the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> was, as appears in the fourth article of his ſecond impeachment or accuſation that he ſhould declare and ſay, That Ireland was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Nation, and that the King might doe with them what he pleaſed; and is not here as much ſpoken, and more by theſe two traiterous ſpirits, <hi>Harvy</hi> and <hi>Solloway?</hi> For Ireland was indeed a Nation by us conquered, and his ſpeech related to the King, who was their head, and had a power over them: but theſe mens words are ſpoken of us a free People, who though formerly conquered, yet have not long ſince redeemed our liberties with our ſwords, and relate to a company of men, who are but ſubjects, and the Kingdomes ſervants, only cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and choſen to coancell and adviſe; not to reign and tyrannize. But let u argue it, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Courts in the Land whatſoever, have rules of jurisdiction and limmits, and hath the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court of Parliament none? It is very unſeaſonable even againſt all rule of reaſon, that that Court which preſeribes rules to all other Courts, ſhould be without all rule it ſelf. The Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Cook,</hi> in his treatiſe of the jurisdiction of the high Court of Parliament declares, and proves otherwiſe: and I am certain that it is againſt the very conſtitution and being of it, for there is both<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Cooks</hi> Inſtituts, Rotu. Parli.</note> 
               <hi>(Lex &amp; conſuetudo Parliamenti)</hi> both a Law and a cuſtome, or uſage of Parliament, Beſides there is a fundamental Law of the Land, againſt which the Parliament cannot (that is lawfully a Parliament) act, for whatſoever act is made or done in Parliament that is contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> is void, no Law, and not to bee<note n="*" place="margin">See 42. Ed. 3. chap. 1.</note> obeyed (and what force then if well examined are moſt of our preſent Parliament Votes. Orders and Ordinances<note n="*" place="margin">But new Lords new laws.</note>) by which it is evident that the Parliament is not without a law and rule, nor may doe what they will, nor any thing (onely in caſe of extremity, and then alſo for good of the publicke, and not unto example) contrary to the fundamentall Lawes and conſtitutions of the Kingdome. And was not one <hi>Wentworth</hi> of the Houſe of Commons queſtioned, yea, and committed in the daies of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for his words and deeds in the Houſe? And can they themſelves deny but that for Treaſon, ſellony, and breach of the Peace, they are queſtionable By all which it is clear, that the proudeſt of them may be queſtioned, and is accountnable for any miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or illegall unjuſt act done by them within the Houſe. They ſay to queſtion them for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing out of the Houſe, is a breach of their priviledge: and muſt we queſtion them neither in the Houſe? What is a Parliament man lawleſſe? Neither without nor within? there is a new priviledge (as their Ordinances are a new manner of Lawes) it was not ſo of old. The King who is the Supreme head, is not without the Law, hee may not de what he liſt: Sure then much leſſe may they, who are but ſubjects and only coucnellers not Commanders, Servants not Maſters. But is not this ſtrange doctrine, my friends, that a Parliament man muſt not be queſtioned for whatſoever he doth in the Houſe? Lo here is a new Hidra-headed prerogative for you to ſuppreſſe, which ye nevner expected. Lop it betimes: for this poſition, tends directly to the ſubverſion of all our Laws and liberties, and the exaction of an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary rule over us. And if this Vote be not treaſonable what is? For by this rule they may within the Houſe, conſult, contrive and act high Treaſon againſt King and Kingdome, commit murder, pick pockets, and breake the peace, deviſe and conſpire to deſtroy and maſſacre us, to rob and ſpoile us, and not to be queſtioned: becauſe it was reſolved, and done within the Houſe. Brave Parliamentary principles!</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61874:9"/>
            <p>Is it not more then high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llow Commoners to rouze up our Spirits, and beſtirre us, to bring ſuch as are the authors and promoters of theſe and ſuch like deſtructive councels and actions to condigne puniſhment? ſhall not the Judge of all the world (ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi>) do right? and ſhall not the Court of Courts, the ſupreme Court of all the Kingdom (we may ſay) do right? Woe is to us, for lamentable is our caſe; our ſtream m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt needs be puddle and dirt, when our very fountain is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilthy and corrupt: <hi>(Corruptio optima eſt paſſima)</hi> that which is beſt, being corrupted is the worſt: that which was formerly Englands Balſum and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote, is now become Englands greateſt Coraſive and poyſon: yet not in it ſelfe, but by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, through the boundles of ambition, and inſatiable avarice of a company of traiterous perſons in both Houſes of Parliament; the chief of which are <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and <hi>Stamford, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton</hi> and <hi>Hollis, Merrick</hi> and ſome others, who have run themſelves by their wicked deeds againſt the King and Common-Wealth, into a deſperate condition; and therefore endeavour by all meanes to bring the Land into a confuſion, and ſo to make our latter end worſe then our beginning: This <hi>Stapletoas</hi> Speech vereſies, who lately ſaid, (I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s now come to this, that either we muſt ſinke them, (meaning the Army) and their friends, or they ſink us;) unto this end it ſeems they have ſo highly provoked the Army: For prevention of which cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and to procure our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe and remedy, we muſt take them away, charge them home and demand their perſons to be delivered up to juſtice: why feare we? what power hath any Parliament man, that he hath not received from them that choſe him? And it a King ſo ſoon as he ceaſeth to rule by the known Law, doth degenerate into a Tyrant, and is worthy to be ejected; what are thoſe Parliament men, <hi>Mancheſter, Hollis, Stapleton</hi> and others of this Faction, who have ſo probably, contrary to their Oaths, Truſts and Duties, left all rule of Law and Juſtice, and by their power and prevalency have dealt with us, and diſpoſed of our eſtates and liberties, after their owne wicked, crooked wils? and what are theſe men worthy of according to law and reaſon? expulſion is too little, and beheading is too honourable: But happily ſome of them may ſay by mee, becauſe I declare that which they no wayes colour, that I am mad; I am ſure they are, &amp; their madneſſe doth appear to all men, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſome of them would not have ſo baſely reproached his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> (who came to London only becauſe of his diſeaſe, &amp; ſtaid there a while for his infirmity and weaknes) in ſaying it was fitter for him to be with his Army, which is in a diſtemper, then to be in Hide Park courting of Ladies. If the Army be diſtempered, hath not <hi>Mancheſter, Stapleton, Hollis</hi> and that turbulent faction diſtempered them, by their im-parliamentary Declaration againſt them, and ingratefull abuſe of them? Nay, do they not diſtemper and trouble the Parliament, and whole Kingdom? are not they the only obſtructers of our ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in England, and of the reliefe of diſtreſſed Ireland? are not theſe I ſay the cauſe of all our diſtraction and diſturbance? I wiſh they were not; and as for Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his courting of Ladies, I would Sir <hi>Peter Temple,</hi> Sir <hi>John M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ck,</hi> Sir <hi>John Hipſly,</hi> M. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, Moore, Bell, Brwyer,</hi> and too many more among them, did not more court Harlots, viſit Whores, and exerciſe drunkenneſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Foth what a ſtinke is here. Oh ſweet Reformers.</note> and other baſeneſs, then honourable Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> worthy man doth delight in courting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ladies? I do remember when the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and his chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Commanders, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrick,</hi> (one of the trayterous crew) and the reſt, came to London, to laze, ſmoake Tobacco and drinke ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, court. complement, vaunt and vapour of that they never did, and a potent enemy at hand in the field, who came up to Brainford, to the hazzard of the whole Army and City before they were diſcovered, and no Chief Officer there, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to command, or deliver forth<note n="*" place="margin">Thanks falſe <hi>Merrick,</hi> thou didſt the like and worſe at Edge-hill.</note> Ammunition: and when not only the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall but all the chief Officers, while there was a deſtroying enemy in power abroad, came and ſtaid their own time in London, to revell, ramble, and rore, drink, domineer and whore, while the ſouldier was left without reſtriction or order, to range, raven and plunder, ſpoile and make waſte, at St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and in the Country thereabouts, and no complaint made of diſtemper, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, either by the Houſe or any of their Members: but the Proverb is, that ſome may better ſteale a Horſe, then others look over the hedge. If Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his Officers
<pb facs="tcp:61874:9"/>or ſouldiers were like wicked Col. Graves, then this evill Faction might ſay they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered indeed: yet this lewd ſhameleſſe man is Stapletons onely Minion, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Inſtrument, (as truely moſt fit for their wicked purpoſe) in the Army, for this mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, malevolent party: but theſe men like Toads are ſo big ſwoln with pride and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite, that they are ready to burſt; and their poyſon will never be purged out, nor we freed from the diffuſed venome of it, till ſome of them be highly exalted, and made an example. Take away the wicked from the King (ſaith Solomon) and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe: take away the wicked and trayterous out of both Houſes of Parliament, and the Parliament ſhall be upright, and proſper, and we poore Commons be ſoon eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in peace and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>In the Book of Declarations, pag. 207. they ſeem to cleare themſelves of a charge laid upon them by the King, ſaying: That there was no colour, that they went about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a new Law, much leſſe to exerciſe<note n="*" place="margin">Marke.</note> an arbitrary power, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. How true this taxe or charge hath ſince proved, let the whole Land judge, and their own actions witneſſe: for if they have not brought in a new Law, I am ſure they have made no uſe of the old, unleſſe it hath been for evill. And whether they have exerciſed an Arbitrary power, I need not aske the queſtion, for it is paſt doubt or ſcruple. But they ſay in the ſame Declaration, That this Law is as old as the Kingdome, to wit, That the Kingdome muſt not be without a meanes to preſerve it ſelfe. It is well (yet truely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.) By their own principle you ſee, the naturall or reall body politique, in caſe the Repreſentative, or virtuall faile, and deceive their truſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Mark and make u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of it.</note> hath power to preſerve it ſelfe: Marke yee free Commons of England, here is a ſure ground for yee to ſtand on, yee are not yet paſt hope, nor deſtitute of meanes of helpe: therefore cheere up your ſpirits, and quit your ſelves like men: imploy and improve your juſt powers, for the preſervation of your ſelves againſt all thoſe ſelfe-ſeeking, ambitious, trayterous, tyrannicall ſpirits in both Houſes; who have forſworn themſelves, betrayd their truſt, and imployed all their power and intereſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with yee intruſted them, for your good and ſafety, to your woe and miſery: And yee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Houſe of Commons, whoſe hearts have ever been upright, (although yee have been awed and overpowered) to God, your King, and Countrey; beware of theſe ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who would involve you in the ſame treaſonable workes with them, that ſo they like Pick-pockets, may the better ſcape in a crowd unſeen: rather proteſt againſt them, and their proceedings; and declare them to the Kingdome, ſerve them as they have ſerved o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: thus yee will acquit your ſelves of jealouſies, and guilt, diſcharge your truſt and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and endeare your ſelves to your Countries: otherwiſe you muſt expect to ſuffer as partakers, and to undergoe the conſure of confederates, and compactours: Sure and ſtable is this principle, (Salus populi eſt ſuprema L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x, The welfare and ſafety of the People is the ſupream Law: and therefore where this end is by Truſtees perverted or neglected, the People by the Law of Nature have power to preſerve and ſecure themſelves: and as certaine is that Rule, that (Major qui facit, quàm quod fit: He which makes is greater then that which is made, and therefore is to be preferred: and in caſe that which is made prove uſeleſſe, hurtfull, or unprofitable, he which makes hath power to modifie, reſtraine, remove, or nullifie, even as ſeemeth good unto him, and may moſt conduce to his good and benefit: And therefore in caſe we cannot receive juſtice from the Parliament, let us force our powers, and apply our ſelves, my friends and fellow Commoners, to have juſtice upon the Authors of our injuſtice and oppreſſions? and no longer ſtand ſtill like People without life and ſpirit, and ſuffer our juſt and reaſonable demands and requeſts to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſted and deſpiſed, as dung or dirt; our Petitions for liberty and juſtice, to be illegally
<pb facs="tcp:61874:10"/>cenſured and ſentenced to be burnt, as ſome horrid, treaſonable and blaſphemous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or papers, and our neighbours, friends, and fellow Commoners, to be tyrannical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impriſoned, and barbarouſly uſed before our eyes, for ſtanding up in the behalfe of the Kingdome, and petitioning for our native and lawfull rights and liberties; by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate wicked party of falſe perfidious men in both Houſes, Machiavilians and Traytors: whoſe Votes and Counſels, waies and workings, tend onely to ſecure their guilty carcaſes from juſtice, and to enſlave and deſtroy us, and our rights and freedomes, who have no feare of the Lord before them, nor any compaſſion or tender reſpect to their native Country this deſtreſſed Nation.</p>
            <p>And now yee grave and wealthy Citizens of the Presbyterian faction, whoſe eyes are ſwoln with fatneſſe, and whoſe hearts with pride and ambition: who happily according to the generall fortune of the great men of London, are endued with a greater portion of riches, ſtate and preſumption, then of prudence, integrity or wiſedome: Give me leave to tell you an Itinerant ſtory, or a parabolicall tale of two Travellers: There were two Travellers met upon the road, and paſſed friendly a long time in ſilence together; at length they diſcover to each other whither they are going, and the end and intention of their travell, and the way they would walke, and they agreed both in one mind, and upon one thing, and ſo they ratifie their aſſociation and friendſhip; but the one was not onely wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but ore-weakned (at leaſt he ſo appeared) both in ſtrength and purſe, by reaſon of his long journey, and the many difficulties and dangers hee had already incountered, and overcome, and very knowing was hee of the way that was yet to be travelled, and of the dangers and difficulties which would oppoſe them therein, before they ſhould come to their journies end: the other albeit he had come as farre, yet by reaſon hee was through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well furniſhed and provided of monies and all needfull ſupplies at his firſt ſetting forth, did retaine the more ability and ſtrength, and had the moſt monies for his ſupport throughout: but alas he was not ſo knowing in the way, nor skilfull as the other, to avoid the dangers therein: whereupon he promiſeth the other aſſiſtance with his purſe, and ſtrength, to carry him through all ſtraits, till they come to their journies end, ſo that he would be aiding and aſſiſting to him with his counſell and advice, for the ſuppreſſing and paſſing of thoſe oppoſitions and perills, which were in the way yet unpaſſed; both agreed rejoyced, and on they journied, with all reciprocall officiouſneſſe, and reſpect each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (the weake man hee wanted not ſupply or ſupport, the other hee wanted no comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words, counſell, or politick advice) untill after many extremities and ſtraights paſt, they came to the laſt and greateſt; and that was a ſteep craggie mountaine; full of ſtraight paſſages, ſlippery by waies, and dubious windings, with deſperate precipices on each ſide; the faire and ſafe way which led to a better end, lying direct in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. Here theſe two Travellers were put to a ſtand, the weak wearied man was not able of himſelf to aſcend, the other notwithſtanding his ſtrength, durſt not adventure alone, leſt hee ſhould ſlip and fall, or loſe his way, and become a prey at length; the weak man lends the other his ſtaffe to ſtay him up, and defend him, and the ſtrong man by his ſtrength takes up the weake, and ſo they both with much hazzard and trouble gat up to the top of this inacceſſible Mountaine; and now they might ſee the long deſired end of their journey, and themſelves paſt all danger, which made them both glad, and to congratulate:<note n="*" place="margin">Obſerve.</note> But the weary weak man, having now been brought at the charge and by the ſtrength and ſupport of the other, through all ſtraites and difficulties, and knowing himſelfe to be much in arreare to his friendly fellow Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and that hee would expect ſatisfaction and recompence, and like beneficence from him, when they were at reſt, and all things were accompliſhed: Hee tooke his ſtaffe from
<pb facs="tcp:61874:10"/>him, (which hee had lent him for a ſtay and defence unto him untill hee had carried him up the hill) and taking an occaſion to quarrell with him, about ſome ſlip, denyall of ſome monies, or neglect of his advice, fell upon him and beate him, bound him, and robbed him of his money and treaſure, and ſo left him in the middeſt of a thicket, deſtitute and ſo deſtroyed and undone. The weake weary man yee may ſuppoſe to be the Parliament: The ſtronger and better provided, to be the wiſe Lord Major, Aldermen, and Common-councel-men, with the reſt of the Presbyteriall faction in London: The Mountaine to be the Presbyters deſigne: and the Staffe to be the Militia, which is now put into the hands of the Presbyterian party in London. The application I leave to the apprehenſion of them, and of all judicious Citizens, and Commoners of England. And will conclude with wiſe Solomon, There is no new thing under the Sunne: that which hath been is now: And what is there that hath been, which may not be againe? Praemoniti praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti, forewarned halfe armed, and (praeviſa minus laedunt) things fore-ſeen doe leſſe hurt. I wiſh you really well, yee grave Citizens of London, both for your owne and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſake; and God make you diſcerning and wiſe, that yee may not by the diſſembling epiſtles and ſpeeches of a deceitfull hypocriticall Nation, and the ſubtill ſophiſtry of an ambitious aſpiring party in both Houſes of Parliament, ſuch as Stapleton, Hollis, &amp;c. and of the proud, covetous Clergy, be made the inſtruments (after you have ſerved their turnes) of your owne ruine and the Lands.</p>
            <p>I could here take occaſion (as there is good reaſon, howſoever what is for preſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted, is not forgot) to ſhew you (deare friends and fellow Commoners) how yee have been abuſed and betrayed, by this very party and faction in both Houſes, their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and inſtruments from the beginning at Sherborne, Northampton, Worceſter, Edgehill, Kingſton, Brainford, Newarke, Exeter, Reading, Thame, (O Thame) the Devizes, Chalgrove field, (where<note n="*" place="margin">S. Philip Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton was there alſo, and beheld afar off; 'twas he that would not ſuffer the queens Regiment to be charged at Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury or Bland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</note>noble Hambden, it is conceived, and who knoweth but it may in time be proved, was delivered to death?) Lincolne, Boſton, Crowland, Cornwall, Dening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Caſtle, (where Mancheſter acted Treaſon) Newarke againe, and Oxford: Durham, Cumberland, Weſtmerland, even in every place, and all along, untill the Lord raiſed up Sir Thomas Fairfax to be a Saviour to the People, and that he is ſo theſe wicked men are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But me thinkes I already ſee this ſerpentine brood (like the old Serpent) caſting a ſtood out after me to deſtroy me, and their defiled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences being like the Sea troubled: they ſend forth mire and dirt; wrath, and revenge, reproaches, curſes, beagles, and blood hounds, Votes, Orders and Meſſengers, like the Popes execrations, with bell, book, and candle. Alas, bene la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet qui bene vivit. I wiſh theſe miſcreants (for their ſoules ſakes) had no more cauſe to be afraid then I. The righteous is as bold as a Lyon, but the wicked ſlees when none pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues. The theeſe thinks every buſh, and every bulk a Conſtable, and a gaulled horſe hath no patience when his ſore is rubbed: this Sir Philip Stapleton knowes, for he hath good skill in horſe-fleſh. But ſeeing theſe vile men will dare to ſinne openly, and to deale falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the World, why ſhould we be afraid to reprove them openly, and to declare it to the World? They declare their ſins as Sodome, they hide them not. Iſai. 3.9. they have (as the Scripture ſpeaks) a brazen face, and a Whores fore-head; and why ſhould wee be ſilent, and connive at that which all Chriſtendome ſees, or turne our backes, and be pymps and panders to our owne ruines? Why ſhould wee be more afraid (whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes) to publiſh their robbery, oppreſſion, injuſtice, and Treaſon, then they are to act and execute it contrary to their Oathes and duties?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61874:11"/>
            <p>Our Law condemnes no man for ſaying the Cole is blacke, or calling a Spade a Spade, although of late many have been<note n="*" place="margin">Marke.</note> impriſoned and puniſhed for no more, nor other thing in effect: yet the looſer will ſpeake, and the oppreſſed will cry out: nor by the power of heaven ſhall my tongue be ſilent, or my Penne be ſlack, for the cauſe of God and this miſerable Land; untill they doe ſet themſelves in a way that is right, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute juſtice and judgement.</p>
            <p>Is it not more then high time to ſpeak and ſtirre, when our juſt and lawfull Petitions are not onely rejected, but infamouſly burned as ſeditious our inveterate Enemies armed, our perſons for preſenting our grievances, illegally impriſoned: when we are voted out of our Rights and Priviledges contrary to all Law and cuſtome of Parliament. All men may now ſee, and plainly underſtand, that it is altogether vaine, any longer to uſe Petitioning, for that due right and liberty is denied and debarred. Wee muſt, I ſay wee muſt, if wee will recover our ſelves and our Priviledges, uſe action. Neceſſity hath no law, and extream danger driveth to extream meanes.</p>
            <p>And now know for certaine, yee Trayterous party, yee falſe deceiptfull men, whoſe hearts are ſet upon wickedneſſe, and whoſe heads deviſe miſchiefe, and violence, that it is not you:<note n="*" place="margin">Such works, ſuch waies, and meanes.</note> breaking open of houſes, taking away mens goods by force, ſpoyling of Printing Preſſes, and impriſoning of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without proofe or cauſe, and puniſhing poore ſoules, who carry Bookes to ſell, will or can hide your ſhame, the day of your judgement is coming: your wickedneſſe is manifeſt as the Sunne, and your actions both publique and private are ſo abominable, that they ſtink in every reaſonable mans noſtrills: yee are become odious, and have made your ſelves a reproach and a hiſſing, and the very abjects of diſdain and ſcorne, yea, inſomuch that the name of a Parliament man, is as contemptible in the thoughts of moſt, as the name is generally of a Committee-man. And thus doe the good and virtuous of the Houſe, ſuffer in their repute and eſteeme, by your vitiouſneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, your beloved friends and favourites cannot juſtifie you, nor open their mouthes clearly for yee, and what will yee doe? what can yee do when God ſhall ſtirre up the People to revenge? Remember Strafford and Canterbury, Finch, and Windebanke: Yee have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the People, and falſified your truſt to them: yee have broken oathes, promiſes, and all manner of aſſurances with them, under a pretence of redeeming their liberties, and making them free, yee involved them in an unnaturall and blood Warre againſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and now yee your ſelves exerciſe more abundant tyrannie, and keep them in moſt ſtrict and intolerable ſlavery, under the pretence of paying the Souldiers, yee have by your Committees, and inſtruments, oppreſſed and robbed the Countries; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is no Army paid, no reparations made, no debts ſatisfied, and thouſands of Widowes and fatherleſſe and maimed ſouldiers unprovided for: under pretence of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the people, yee have deſtroyed them, and under the colour of eſtabliſhing Law and juſtice, yee have taken away both: and although yee raiſed Armes to redeem the King from his wicked Councell, and have ſolemnly ſworn to maintaine his Crowne and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and declared Book Dec. pag. 94. that what you did was for his honour and greatneſſe, and the weale of his Kingdomes. Yet though hee be redeemed, hee is not reſtored, not is his Crowne and dignity maintained: Nay yee your ſelves exerciſe the Kingly office; yee, I ſay it againe, yee your ſelves exerciſe the Kingly office: For ye make Lord Keepers,<note n="*" place="margin">Without the King meer treaſon, and without his aſſent worſe then nothing.</note> Judges and Barons, grant Pardons, and give Commiſſions of Oyer and Terminer: I have known a mean man dye as a traytor for doing leſſe: nor are the Acts or Proceſs paſſed under the broad Seale of any value: In all which yee are but uſurpers (I ſhould not miſtake if I ſaid Traytors) I ſay
<pb facs="tcp:61874:11"/>uſurpers, and take too much upon you; for by Law there is no ſuch power or right belonging to you, or inveſted in yee: You keep the King under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and with-hold him from the execution of it, and doe not ſatisfie the World wherefore ye doe it: you are like the Dog in the manger, which will neither let the horſe eat the hay, nor eat it himſelf: yee will neither admit the King to do juſtice, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe our grievances, nor will yee your ſelves: yee have made no other uſe of the Kings power and name, then to deceive, oppreſſe, and abuſe the People.</p>
            <p>Is this to doe for his honour and greatneſſe, and the good of his Kingdomes? contrarium verò eſt verum, the contrary is true, by true.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not in favour of his Majeſtie further then conſcience and<note n="*" place="margin">Doe unto all men as yee would be done unto.</note> equity, the Lord my Maker knows I am ſincerely for truth and juſtice, without partiality, and againſt the contrary, whereſoever, or in whomſoever I find it: but a traytor or felon by the Law looſeth not any of his franchizes, poſſeſſions and eſtate, before he be convict: let Ceſar have his due, and us the free Commons ours: if not, I doubt not, but you will in due time have yours: If the King be King let him raigne: if he have otherwiſe deſerved, why proceed ye not legally againſt him, that the World may ſee and judge, and ye be cleared of all calumny and aſperſion? But as you dee, and deale with us, ſo ye deale with him: Us ye doe unjuſtly impriſon and oppreſſe, rob, and ſpoyle, deſtroy our Liberties, take away our eſtates, and undoe our Families, and ſhew us no Law, Cauſe or Reaſon, but a tyrannicall, unjuſt, ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, or treaſonable Vote, Order, or Ordinance: (Sic vultis, ſic jubet's, ſtat pro ratione voluntas:) Your Arbitrary wills are become Englands Lawes.</p>
            <p>And would yee know, yee Commons of England, why the King is not in all this time b ought home, nor any thing reſolved nor determined of him? I will tell you (deare friends) what I conceive I ſee: The Earle of Mancheſter, M. Hollis, Stapleton, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are abſolutely the chiefe inſtrumentall cauſes of all the evils, wee have lately ſuffered, and doe ſtill ſuſtaine, and ſome of which have received vaſt ſummes of monies, whereof they know themſelves unable to give any good account, are in danger to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as traytors and deceivers, and be ſacrificed to juſtice: and therefore through their power, prevalency, and policy, a ſettlement between King and Parliament is deferred: becauſe by reaſon of the Army, whoſe integrity and zeale for juſtice they feare (and therefore onely would disband them) they cannot impoſe ſuch particular, peculiar condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon the King, as will fully ſecure them, and conduce to their Presbyterian deſigne: this I doe beleeve, is the ſumme of all. But muſt the King and his People be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll divided, the breach lye open, and the difference uncompoſed, the Kingdome unſetled, the peoples p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace and happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe ſtill delayed, and our miſeries ſtill prolonged and continued, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the unjuſt deſires of a company of matchleſſe Machiavilian traytors, who to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, have endeavoured by all meanes to deſtroy us? Muſt wee languiſh in our ſufferings and ſorrowes to waite their opportunities? It is neither meet nor right it ſhould be ſo, nor prudence nor wiſedome to permit it ſo, let us therefore have an end of our troubles and diſtractions, or elſe apply our ſelves to put an end to their tyranny, treaſon, and Lordlineſſe, that they may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wholly and utterly lay us waſte and ruine us. And if in caſe of the Kings failing of his truſt, and denyall to ſettle the Militia or ſtrength of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in ſuch hands, and in ſuch a way, as the people may be thereby ſafe and ſecured, the Parliament (the repreſentative body) may for the ſafety of his Majeſty, and Kingdomes, take the diſpoſe and ordering of it into their hands: then by the ſame rule, forſomuch as the Parliament have failed of their truſt, and put the Militia and ſtrength of the Kingdome into ſuch hands, and in ſuch a way, as wee cannot confide or be ſafe in: Wee the free
<pb facs="tcp:61874:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Commons of England, the reall and eſſentiall body politicke, or any part of us, may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and diſpoſe of our owne Armes and ſtrength, for our owne preſervation and ſafety; and the Army in particular (without queſtion) may lawfully retaine, order and diſpoſe of their armes and ſtrength, to and for the preſervation and ſafety of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the principall end for which they were raiſed. This is the Parliaments owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as you may read in Booke Declarations page 93. and 150. and therefore I hope neither hereſie nor ſchiſme, blaſphemy nor treaſon. I have done, and a ruſh for him that is angry, and as much for him who is fearefull in a juſt cauſe: Let ſuch weigh well that ſaying of the holy Spirit, Prov. 29.25. and then happily they may looke up and take courage: The feare of man bringeth a ſnare, but whoſoever truſteth in the Lord ſhall be ſafe. (Timida probl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as nunquam Reipublicae eſt utilis.) Cowardly honeſty is never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
